[Music]
foreign
the number one killer in the United
States and around the world is what we
eat killing Millions more than tobacco
for example what are the five most
important things we can do to improve
our diets based on the single most
comprehensive Global study the health
impact of nutrition eat less salt eat
more nuts eat more non-starchy
vegetables and more fruit and finally
eat more whole grains any particular
type of whole grains what about
so-called Ancient Grains are they any
better than modern varieties uh like
what about camut the so-called mummy
wheat supposedly Unearthed from an
Egyptian tomb after World War II the
wheat industry selected particularly
High yielding varieties for pasta and
bread over the past few years though
some of the more ancient varieties have
been reintroduced on the market find
basically as those that you know haven't
changed over the agricultural
Revolutions of last century
nutritionally Ein corn wheat the oldest
wheat and Camo have more of the eyesight
improving yellow carotenoid pigments
like lutein and zeaxanthin compared to
Modern bread and pastry wheat because
the pigments have been bred out of the
bread intentionally people want their
white bread white but modern pasta flour
durum wheat maintains much of that
yellow Hue nutrition
yes modern wheat may have less lutein
but for example tends to have more
vitamin E based on straight vitamin and
mineral concentrations I mean it's
pretty much a wash they both have lots
of each but the Primitive weeds do have
more antioxidant capacity likely due to
their greater polyphenol content but you
know to know if this makes any
difference you have to put it to the
test if you expose human liver cells to
digested bread made out of Ancient
Grains camutin spelled Heritage wheat or
modern strains and then expose the cells
to an inflammatory stimulus the modern
wheat strains seem less able to suppress
the inflammation the investigators
conclude that you know despite the fact
that these different grains seem to be
very similar nutritionally they seem to
exert different effects on human cells
confirming the potential health benefits
of Ancient Grains
but this was in a Petri dish what about
in people
if ancient Wheats are better at
suppressing inflammation what if you
took people with irritable bowel
syndrome and randomized them to receive
six weeks of wheat products made out of
the ancient wheat kamut in this case or
modern wheat um same amount of wheat
just different types if there's no
difference between the Wheats there'd be
no difference in people's symptoms right
but check this out here's how the
control groups did on the modern wheat
switch to the camo they experienced less
abdominal pain less frequent pain less
bloating a more satisfaction with stool
consistency and less interference with
their quality of life so after switching
to the ancient grain patients
experienced a significant Global
Improvement in the extent of severity of
symptoms related to their irritable
bowel
what about liver inflammation the liver
function of those with non-alcoholic
fatty liver disease randomized to eat
camo improved compared to those eating
the same amount of regular wheat the
suggests in chemma is Superior in
diabetics better cholesterol and insulin
sensitivity on the same ancient grain in
those with heart disease better blood
sugar control and better cholesterol
better artery function in those without
overt heart disease the bottom line is
findings derived from Human studies
suggests that ancient wheat products are
more anti-inflammatory and improve
things like blood sugar control and
cholesterol
given that the overall number of human
Interventional trials is still small and
it's not possible to definitively
conclude that ancient wheat varieties
are superior to all commercial modern
wheat counterparts and reducing chronic
disease risk but uh the best available
data does suggest they're better if if
you have the choice regardless of what
type of wheat you eat word to the wise
don't eat the plastic bread bag clip 45
year old guy presents with bloody stools
and this is what their CT scan looked
like later question the patient admitted
to habitually eating quickly without
chewing properly
[Music]